Guide to the Percival Farquhar Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Percival Farquhar papers
1893-1967
1919-1945
MS 205
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
7.5
The papers consist of the business files and correspondence of Percival Farquhar. They document his role in the economic development of Brazil, in particular the Itabira Iron Ore Company. Correspondents include mining engineer Alexander Malozemoff, businessmen J. F. Trippet and Alexander MacKenzie, and aide J. Armstrong Read. Also included in the papers are the research materials used by Charles Gauld, Farquhar's biographer, in the writing of The Last Titan: Percival Farquhar, American Entrepreneur in Latin America.
Farquhar, Percival, 1864-1953
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Charles Gauld, 1962, 1965-1967.
Biographical / Historical
Percival Farquhar was born in York, Pennsylvania on October 19, 1864. He graduated from Sheffield Scientific School in 1884 and joined his father's New York based export company, which shipped machinery to Latin America. In 1885, Farquhar studied law briefly at Columbia Law School. After serving as an assemblyman in the New York state legislature from 1890 to 1892, he joined a friend's company developing electric railroads and real estate in New Jersey. In 1898, Farquhar began a long career of financial operations in Latin America to modernize tramways. From 1907 to 1914, he directed his attention and resources to the improvement of the ports and railroads of Brazil, in particular, the Madeira-Mamoré Railway and the Port of Para. He also established the Brazil Railway Company. From 1919 to 1941, Farquhar managed the Itabira project, designed to revive the Itabira Iron Ore Company and to build a railway to a new port near Vitória. Thwarted by nationalistic opposition and financial losses, the Itabira project did not succeed in his lifetime. Farquhar died in New York City on August 4, 1953.
Arrangement
Arranged by topic.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of the business files and correspondence of Percival Farquhar. They document his role in the economic development of Brazil, in particular the Itabira Iron Ore Company. Correspondents include mining engineer Alexander Malozemoff, businessmen J. F. Trippet and Alexander MacKenzie, and aide J. Armstrong Read. Also included in the papers are the research materials used by Charles Gauld, Farquhar's biographer, in the writing of The Last Titan: Percival Farquhar, American Entrepreneur in Latin America.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Americans -- Brazil; Railroads -- Brazil; Brazil; Latin America; South America; Biographies (documents); Capitalists and financiers; Farquhar, Percival, 1864-1953; Gauld, Charles Anderson, 1911-; Mackenzie, Alexander; Malozemoff, Andrew, 1910-1952; Read, J. Armstrong; Russell, T. O.; Trippet, J. F.; Brazil Railway Company; Ferrovia Madeira-Mamoré; Itabira Iron Ore Company; Rio de Janeiro Tramway Light and Power Company
- Inventory, 1893-1967
  Scope and Contents
  The papers consist primarily of business records from various companies with which Percival Farquhar was involved. The files attest to Farquhar's entrepreneurial ambitions in Brazil and those for the Itabira Iron Ore Company/Itabira Railway are particularly voluminous. The business papers are arranged alphabetically by company name and may contain correspondence; memoranda; reports; surveys; legal and financial documents; and related items. Farquhar's original arrangement of papers has been maintained. Correspondence with family members, listed alphabetically, is both personal and professional in nature, as Farquhar's family participated in his business ventures. There is also a small amount of memorabilia and photographs. Papers relating to Charles Gauld contain interviews, correspondence, research notes, and drafts compiled for the biography of Farquhar. Unpublished biographical material by Vivaldo Coaracy is also included in the papers.
  - Farquhar, Percival
    - Autobiography ["Notas Autobiográficas"], 1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Business papers
      - General [primarily negotiations with lenders to raise capital], 1928-1943 (Box 1, Folder 2-5)
      - Brazil Railway Company, 1901-1946, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 6-14)
      - Brazil Railway Company, 1932-1943 (Box 2, Folder 15-22)
      - Brazilian Iron Ore Company, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - International Products Corporation, 1931-1942 (Box 2, Folder 24-28)
      - Itabira Iron Ore Company/Itabira Railway
        - 1919-1930 April (Box 3, Folder 29-41)
        - 1930 May-1940 April (Box 4, Folder 42-57)
        - 1940 May-1944 September (Box 5, Folder 58-71)
        - 1919-1945 (Box 6, Folder 72-85)
        - 1920-1942 (Box 7, Folder 86-97)
        - 1920-1943 (Box 8, Folder 98-111)
        - 1920-1946, 1954, 1963 (Box 9, Folder 112-124)
        - 1919-1953, undated (Box 10, Folder 125-136)
        - 1922-1947 (Box 11, Folder 137-150)
        - 1911, 1920-1953 (Box 12, Folder 151-163)
        - 1921-1954, 1963 (Box 13, Folder 164-179)
        - 1927-1953 (Box 14, Folder 180-198)
        - 1933-1943, 1954, 1963 (Box 15, Folder 199-205)
        - 1938 (Box 15, Folder 206)
      - Madeira-Mamoré Railway, 1937-1951 (Box 15, Folder 207)
      - Port of Para, 1906-1943 (Box 15, Folder 208-211)
      - Rio de Janeiro Tramway Light and Power Company, 1935-1954 (Box 15, Folder 212)
    - Correspondence
      - General, 1893, 1929-1953 (Box 16, Folder 213-215)
      - Coaracy, Vivaldo, 1943, undated (Box 16, Folder 216)
        General
        Includes partial draft of unfinished biography of Farquhar.
      - Farquhar, Cathya [wife], 1942-1943 (Box 16, Folder 217)
      - Farquhar, Donald [son], 1939-1953 (Box 16, Folder 218-221)
      - Farquhar, Francis [brother], 1932-1944, 1951, undated (Box 16, Folder 222)
      - Farquhar, George [son], 1930-1939 (Box 16, Folder 223-236)
      - Farquhar, George [son], 1940-1951 (Box 17, Folder 237-241)
      - Farquhar, Gordon [son], 1942-1948 (Box 17, Folder 242)
      - Gomes, Olivo, 1942-1951 (Box 17, Folder 243-244)
    - Memorabilia, 1920, 1929, 1940-1945 (Box 17, Folder 245)
    - Photographs/negatives [includes Farquhar, Itabira], 1913, 1929-[194?], 1950, undated (Box 17, Folder 246-247)
  - Gauld, Charles [correspondence, writings, and research materials, pertaining to the biography of Percival Farquhar], 1915-1967 (Box 18, Folder 248-267)
  - Oversize (Box 19)